{"tossups": [{"question": "This initiative was made possible when one army was given the \u201cHalt Order\u201d and told to withdraw to the Canal Line at Lys. May 26 was declared a national day of prayer out of George VI\u2019s desperation to see this initiative succeed. This initiative, codenamed Operation Dynamo, involved the use of fishing boats and civilian ships, and its end prompted Winston Churchill to give the \u201cWe shall fight on the beaches\u201dspeech. For ten points, name this \u201cmiracle\u201d in which Allied forces were delivered from a namesake French beach in 1940.", "answer": "evacuation from<b> Dunkirk</b> (<b>Dunkirk</b> is all that is needed; accept Operation<b> Dynamo</b> before mentioned; prompt on descriptive answers related to evacuating France in 1940, escaping the Nazis,", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During an October 1967 protest at this facility, George Harris placed carnations in the barrels of soldiers\u2019 guns. In 2010, Jeffrey Amos was one of two policeman shot by John Patrick Bedell at this facility\u2019s underground Metro station. The Phoenix Project helped repair this facility after Hani Hanjour and four others hijacked American Airlines Flight 77 and crashed it into this facility. For ten points, name this Arlington County, Virginia facility that houses the Department of Defense?", "answer": "the<b> Pentagon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, one perpetrator was caught on camera wearing a shirt that said \u201cLOL.\u201d The victim of this event had, in 2001, fallen out with his family after using a fake passport to try to visit Disneyland Tokyo. The perpetrators of this event sprayed the nerve agent VX in the victim\u2019s face, having been told they were filming a scene for a prank TV show. For ten points, name this February 2017 incident at an airport in Kuala Lumpur that led to tensions between Malaysia and North Korea.", "answer": "the<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> death</b>, etc.) of<b> Kim Jong-Nam</b> (prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptions of \u201cthe assassination of Kim Jong-Un\u2019s (half)-brother\u201d or \u201cthe assassination of Kim Jong-il\u2019s son\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man espoused his hate for Catholics in the book <em>Foreign Conspiracy Against the Liberties of</em> <em>the United States</em>. Chemistry professor Leonard Gale helped this man perfect his most famous invention, which was boosted by Maine congressman Francis O.J. Smith\u2019s funding for a 38-mile-long structure from Washington D.C. to Baltimore that transmitted the words \u201cWhat hath God wrought\u201d in 1844. For ten points, name this American inventor of the single-wire telegraph system.", "answer": "Samuel Finley Breese<b> Morse</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s troops killed tens of thousands of Greeks by burning down Smyrna while attempting to restore lost territories during the Chanak Crisis. This man\u2019s government rejected the Treaty of Sevres in favor of the 1923 Treaty of Lausanne. He promoted the Six Arrows ideology, which created a new modern alphabet based on Latin and banned the wearing of the fez in an attempt to westernise his newly formed republic. For ten points, name this founder of modern Turkey.", "answer": "Mustafa<b> Kemal Ataturk</b> (accept either or both underlined names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A life size nude depicting a female Greek one of these people holds a small cross in a marble sculpture by Hiram Powers. Juan de Pareja was one of these people who himself became an artist after he was painted by Diego Velazquez. Two sculptures, later identified as these people rather than prisoners, were intended to flank a horned sculpture of Moses for the tomb of Pope Julius II. For ten points, name this type of person who Michelangelo showed bound to rocks as part of their forced labor.", "answer": "<b> slave</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This character\u2019s implicit offer of marriage is declined by a man who states that he, like his prized rooks, can only fall in love once in his lifetime. The actress who plays Clara Oswald on<em> Doctor Who</em> also plays this character, who is remorseful after spreading rumors about the illegitimate pregnancy of Flora Hastings only to discover she has stomach cancer instead. After ascending to the throne, this woman distances herself from her mother, the Duchess of Kent, and she elects to marry the Saxon Prince Albert. Jenna Coleman portrays, for ten points, which British monarch who ruled for most of the 19th century?", "answer": "<b> Victoria</b> (accept<b> Alexandrina</b> Victoria)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "As chief justice, this man upheld a fine against two brothers who had tried to sell federal lottery tickets outside the District of Columbia in the case<em> Cohens v. Virginia</em>. This man\u2019s legal career vaulted when he argued the losing side in the Supreme Court case of<em> Ware v. Hylton</em>. This man\u2019s court held that land sales could not be voided despite the Yazoo scandal in Georgia in the case of<em> Fletcher v. Peck</em>. For ten points, name this Chief Justice from 1801 to 1835.", "answer": "John<b> Marshall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One composer from this country co-wrote the<em> Cantiones Sacrae</em> with his mentor and collected virginal music in<em> My Ladye Nevelles Booke</em> after receiving a 21-year monopoly on music publishing from this country\u2019s monarch. Another composer from this country wrote the forty-voice motet<em> Spem in Alium</em> and a psalm tune that Ralph [rafe] Vaughan Williams adapted into a<em> Fantasia</em>. For ten points, name this county in which William Byrd and Thomas Tallis composed music under Queen Elizabeth.", "answer": "<b> England</b> (accept<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom; accept Great<b> Britain</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An ancient landslide that temporarily dammed this river is known in Native American legends as the Bridge of the Gods, and occurred near its present-day Bonneville Lock and Dam. A fishing community along its Celio Falls was disrupted by the construction of a dam at The Dalles, and its longest tributary flows past Idaho Falls and Boise. The Snake River flows into, for ten points, what river that forms part of the border between Washington and Oregon?", "answer": "<b> Columbia</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man was made governor of Magnesia after accusations that he had conspired with the traitor Pausanias forced him to flee his hometown. This man used the spy Sicinnus to bait an enemy fleet into fighting in the Saronic Gulf. In 483 BC, this man convinced his city to use profits from a silver strike at Laurium to build 200 triremes. The power of the Athenian navy grew immensely thanks to, for ten points, what Greek admiral who was victorious at the Battle of Salamis?", "answer": "<b> Themistocles</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Despite having a palsied arm, this man was never assisted in writing by his follower, John Purvey. William Courtenay condemned this man at the \u201cEarthquake Synod.\u201d A follower of a movement founded by this man served as the basis for the Shakespearean character of Falstaff. John Oldcastle believed in this man\u2019s ideas, and he inspired the Czech theologian Jan Hus. For ten points, name this English thinker who attacked the excesses of the clergy as the leader of the Lollards.", "answer": "John<b> Wycliffe</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This event led to the creation of a red-light district known as the Barbary Coast. \u201cCoyoteing\u201d was a technique used in this event, which was first publicized by Samuel Brannan. A businessman opened a dry goods business during this event, then shifted from selling tents to selling denim pants in the 1870s. This event began after James Marshall\u2019s discovery at Sutter\u2019s Mill. A mass emigration of \u201cforty-niners\u201d took place during, for ten points, what 19th century economic \u201crush\u201d on the American West Coast?", "answer": "<b> California Gold Rush</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Omar Mukhtar fought for independence against this empire in the mountains of Jebel Akhdar. This European empire received Tripolitania in the Treaty of Ouchy and signed</b> <b>the Treaty of Wuchale to establish its colony of (+)</b> <b>Eritrea. This empire, which made</b> <b>Mogadishu the capital of its Somaliland, was humiliated after its loss at the Battle of (*) </b>Adwa to Menelek II, but it would get its revenge over Haile Selassie. For ten points, name this European power that colonized Libya and conquered Ethiopia while ruled by Benito Mussolini.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During a meeting with Melih Absel, this man said \u201cThe illegal we do immediately. The unconstitutional takes a little longer.\u201d This man outlined one of his famous strategies in his book</b><em><b> The Necessity for Choice</b></em><b>; that strategy was a response to an earlier policy of (+)\u201cmassive retaliation\u201d and involved a \u201cflexible response\u201d to nuclear threats. This man\u2019s frequent flying between Middle Eastern capitals, attempting to resolve the (*)</b> Yom Kippur War, became known as \u201cshuttle diplomacy.\u201d For ten points, name this proponent of d\u00b4etente who served as Secretary of State under Presidents Ford and Nixon.", "answer": "Henry Alfred<b> Kissinger</b> (or Heinz Alfred<b> Kissinger</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This city was once taken over by the Small Swords Society. An incident within this city, in which Isao Oyama shot an airport guard to death, helped heighten tensions prior to (+) World War II. An international settlement was built in this city after it became the highest profile port to be opened to trade in the Treaty of Whampoa. Most of Jiang Qing\u2019s (*) </b>Gang of Four was based in this city, which is now the site of the international Bund, or Waitan, district. For ten points, name this port city of eastern China, one of the most populous cities in the world.", "answer": "<b> Shanghai</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Thermal voltage is used in a set of three equations describing different currents flowing through these devices in the Ebers-Moll model. Walter Brattain, William Shockley, and John Bardeen (+) invented these devices at Bell Labs and accordingly won the 1956 Nobel in Physics. The MOSFET variety of these devices is now more popular than their bipolar junction type. Moore\u2019s law states that the number of these devices per square inch on an integrated (*)</b> circuit doubles about every two years. For ten points, name these semiconducting devices that amplify electronic signals and were used in a type of namesake radio.", "answer": "<b> transistor</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The three-stratum and CHC theories were formulated in the late 20th-century to explain this concept. This trait\u2019s \u201ccrystallized\u201d form typically increases with age, while its \u201cfluid\u201d</b> <b>form tends to decrease. Raven\u2019s Progressive Matrices and the (+)</b> <b>Wason four-card test</b> <b>are used to evaluate this trait, which was first studied in a psychological sense by Alfred (*) </b>Binet [bin-ay] in 1905. The Flynn effect quantifies the general rise of this quantity in society over time. For ten points, name this concept, the ability to process information and solve problems, often measured and reported via a \u201cquotient\u201d after taking a test.", "answer": "<b> intelligence</b> (accept<b> IQ</b> or<b> intelligence</b> quotient)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1990, this country\u2019s no-party Panchayat system was reformed by King Birendra. After the Battle of Kirtipur, Prithvi Narayan Shah unified this country in 1769. (+) </b> <b>Gyanendra rose to power in this country after a 2001 massacre of the royal family. The April 2015 Gorkha (*) </b> earthquake killed over 9,000 people in this country, including 21 in an avalanche on Mount Everest. For ten points, name this Himalayan country with capital Kathmandu.", "answer": "<b> Nepal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}